so this is the latest rebel wisdom
podcast an exciting one because this
morning I did an interview with Jordan
Peterson which is the second interview
that I've done and the first time I've
seen him since
I saw him last October which we then
turned into the documentary truth from
the time of chaos and then glitch in the
matrix so yeah really exciting - yes I
sort of see where he's at and obviously
the kind of trajectory that he's been on
since then has just been so exponential
and yeah I was really pleased with like
we talked about sort of being a bit
concerned he was getting burnt out and
didn't get a sense of that at all from
from meeting him it was really yeah he
was on good form and I think we got some
really really interesting stuff and
we're going to play some of it in this
podcast referring specifically to the
Sam Harris debates because that just
happened and yeah so he's done four four
debates with Sam Harris now - in
Vancouver one in Dublin one in London on
the subject of religion versus atheism
and the other thing is to kind of look
forward to what else is coming up we
just come back from the u.s. we've got a
huge amount of content some really
exciting stuff we just put out an
interview with Paul van der clay the
kind of pastor from Sacramento who's
becoming kind of a little mini online
celebrity because it was commentaries on
Jordan Pederson
and one person commented the pastor of
the IDW
Paul van der clay officially the pastor
of the IDW congratulations Paul it's now
official three YouTube comments making
the same one makes it actually official
so good so yeah Sam Harris and Jordan
Pederson so I haven't been to any of
these debates
and but we've listened someone's very
sneekly put some of the audio online so
I've listened to some of the stuff in
Vancouver and some of the stuff from
from London a couple of nights ago and
we've also commented quite like we've
been interested ourselves and kind of
this interplay between like we've said
quite a few times for for me for you I
think as well John and Peter Som
represents a kind of potential
reintegration of the sacred grounding in
neuroscience grounding it in mythology
and it's clear that Sam Harris is very
sort of the irony is they're both within
this kind of loose collective called the
IDW but they've clearly got very
different perspectives which I guess is
why so many people have gone to see them
talk over the last kind of four days
from me you know equally listening to
the kind of the bootlegged stuff and
kind of engaging with the debates there
is a sense of something new happening in
the sense that the traditional kind of
new atheist argument has this real focus
on religion almost as a political force
and the kind of irrationality of it and
all of that but some of which I can
engage with some of which I would even
you know agree with but what Peterson
seems to be bringing and what these
debates are kind of exploring is a
different kind of exploration of maybe
what we call the religious impulse
rather than looking specifically at
religion but taking that deeper level
and looking at the impulse within us as
you know the biological historical
cultural impulse in us which is so deep
to be religious creatures and I you know
I feel like Jordan Peterson it's coming
or or reintroducing that into the
culture and Sammis is holding a
different piece which is a kind of
warning against the fundamentalism that
can come about with religion which is a
fair warning definitely but the paradox
that we're going to explore is that that
kind of viewpoint in itself
we could call scientism is in danger of
becoming a fundamental fundamentalism
itself it's not already if not already
and this is something we're going to
explore so we're going to play a clip
now the first one of
first questions I asked Peterson
Peterson about this which was started by
talking about the IDW which we'll put
out at some future time but the what a
lot of people are sensing from the IDW
why it's sort of quite kind of
intellectually dark web for any of that
people haven't been watching our other
stuff is there's a sense of they're
asking really big questions and there's
some really big ideas and great thinkers
in it but ultimately what I think people
are tuning into is a sense of people
thinking in public and a sense of this
is what it looks like for two people to
engage in a generative dialogue around
different ideas and one that sort of
builds so so yeah that's that was the
starting point of this question that
we're going to roll now there's a kind
of intellectual curiosity and a sense of
people thinking in public and and
there's also a sense of maybe the
potential for people to change their
minds or to discover things during the
conversation well that's partly the
appreciation of the intelligence of the
audience it's like and I would say it is
actually the manifestation of the
process of thinking that's more
important than the conclusions that are
generated even in these discussions that
I've been having with Harris like we are
trying to to argue out to different
viewpoints because Harris believes that
values can be derived with with with
unerring precision in some sense using
the proper methodology from facts and I
I believe that it's more complicated
than that that there has to be
intermediating structures and those are
really narrative in in their nature so
there's a technical argument as well as
a variety of sub arguments about the
relative role of traditional religion
and so forth but the outcome of the
debate about those issues is partly what
people are coming to the talks to see to
determine what should the conclusions be
but a much larger part perhaps is to in
to observe and engage at least by proxy
in the process of dialogue and that's
more important because
dialogue is the process by which complex
problems are solved
which is what makes me a free speech
advocate fundamentally was not an
advocate it's like I realized that that
the protection for free speech is
protection of the mechanism whereby
complex social problems are solved and
were were the people in this group and
many other people as well are acting out
that biological process and and people
are happy about that as they should be
based on what Jordan Peterson was just
saying and then also listening to the
pod sort to the debate what really
struck me was was one particular moment
when Sam Harris mentioned you know talks
about the mystical or I don't think he
would refer to this mystical experiences
but the deep experiences he's had
through Buddhism and I believe
psychedelics as well and then he kind of
makes a comment around yeah but I wasn't
sort of Marshall tol'able was the word
but something around that I wasn't kind
of gullible enough to kind of attribute
that to something other than the
workings of my own mind and then Peter
says it says you need to take a bigger
dose and sir it's a great moment in the
debate as well and it really you know
even though it's kind of a fun moment it
also points to maybe for me one of the
deepest aspects of this because in the
debate I get a sense that Harris his his
understanding or his model of religion
that he's putting out is one which is
very much the structured religions and
Andrew Sweeney in a recent piece on
rebel wisdom he mentioned that this
model of a God with like a bearded man
in the sky that the kind of atheist tend
to use is not really the religious
understanding of the model of God that
people who for whom religion is
important part of their lives use no one
who's serious about religion believes
that type of model at all and that's
that's an interesting thing for me
because it gets back to that point of
there's a difference between the
internal experience we have the internal
religious experience which is about
experiencing the transcendent it's not
believing in anything it's no belief
there's no space for belief it's you
have an internal experience that is that
is
religious drive and that is the
religious experience I think Harris is
absolutely right in the sense that you
cannot take that experience I can't have
some deep psychedelic experience if you
like David I've just figured out that
everyone's we're actually earth isn't
earth we're actually all sitting on a
massive green elephant and I really need
everyone to know this so we have really
going to put this out there you can't do
that because science is the language we
use for you and me to agree on what we
can both agree on like look through this
telescope what do you see okay well I
have a hypothesis about it well you're
gonna try and disprove my hypothesis
until we reach a synthesis where we can
be reasonably like really really sure
about what's in that telescope so those
two things they can't cross over and the
integral studies as big on this they
can't cross over but they can coexist so
finally the Petersons point around its
the discourse that's in a sense more
important that really connected with me
when he when he says that because they
could do a thousand debates and they are
never ever going to solve this the
science versus spirituality thing yeah I
mean listening to the recent one at the
o2 you get the sense oof and I guess
you've got the sense since Peterson and
Harris started talking that they're
talking past each other yeah and you
frequently hear Sam accusing Jordan of
not answering the question
and it's interesting listening to that
because I didn't get that sense that
Jordan was him was avoiding the question
like it's interesting I mean I probably
listen to a lot of Jordan Peters and
stuff and listen to quite a lot of sam
Harris's stuff as well like I've got a
lot of respect for the waking up podcast
there was a spectator article this
morning really good spectre article
maybe we'll link to it under this where
the writer was saying he he thinks
Jordan Pederson has a bigger view than
sam Harris that he understands Sam
Harris's perspective better than Sam
Harris's understands Jordan Peterson's
perspective now I think that's true
obviously we've we've done a lot of
stuff about Jordan Peterson and just a
point we did actually ask if sam Harris
would be available for an interview
while he was here in London but he
wasn't
because I'd love to put some of this
stuff to him so Sam if you're watching
we'd love to interview you give you a
chance to respond and but I but I did
get the sense that there was a frequent
kind of reducing to caricature by Sam
Harris that I didn't think I didn't get
that feeling from Peterson Peterson
staff is a huge amount of his his
comments with yes yes but like including
like he includes a lot of what sam says
sam kind of seems to continually reduce
it down to the material or to the human
and peterson says yes and which which is
really interesting because we talk about
integral theory quite a lot in the whole
idea is yes and peterson seems to be yes
handing sam harris an awful lot he's
saying to sam harris is saying we'll
hang on are you saying that this was
divinely inspired how can you tell you
that this book was divinely inspired and
peterson is saying well we don't know
where creativity comes from that in some
sense creativity comes from somewhere we
don't understand and if you take
creativity over millenia where things
are refined and refined and refined what
is kept of that particular story has to
reflect something has to reflect some
kind of divine reality or what it has to
reflect some kind of reality which you
can choose to call divine or not and Sam
continued kind of just brings it back to
know this is just people's imagination
or just this this is just so I do feel
yeah very frequently the Peterson takes
does understand that incorporates Sam
Harris's reductive world view but frames
it within something more and yeah I
think that's a good point another thing
that struck me somehow it actually makes
a really good point towards the end of
the last debate where he says look he
starts talking about consciousness and
our understanding of what consciousness
is and he said you know that could've
been a place we started this particular
debate and they may well have covered
that in the in the first two I'm not
sure if as I've seen them but that is I
think a really key question because
there's you know we talked about the
soft problem of consciousness and the
hard problem and the soft problem is
effectively how is our neurobiology
involved in how we perceive the world
and that's soft because we can do brain
scans and we can look at it and we can
you know we can experiment back and
that out pretty much the hard problem is
what is consciousness and you know is it
local or non-local as in is
consciousness a quality of the universe
which is everywhere and we happen to be
recipients of that really yeah pantheism
effectively or is it specifically just
in the human mind you know all of that
question that has not been answered yet
and it also there is a sense that it
can't be answered yeah so and this is
this is where I keep coming back to the
the sort of my real frustration with the
more strict strict materialist types
because you can't have a worldview that
says well we understand pretty much
everything apart from consciousness like
okay so you can understand absolutely
everything apart from the thing that's
experiencing absolutely everything
that's a pretty big hole in your theory
and to maintain this kind of very
dogmatic materialism without accepting
that this is you you're like okay just
give me that one miracle of the fact
that we can experience anything and then
I'll explain everything it's like no
sorry you're you're asking for a it's a
different kind of because they argue
that religion is sort of miraculous or
magical thinking it's like no actually
you've got a magical thinking going on
as well just the same as believers yeah
that's that's a good point as well and
and not just the magical thinking but
also the the dangers of dogmatism that
can come about not talking about some
heresy necessarily just that what my
experience of very extreme materialists
because I'm one of the organizers of
breaking convention of psychedelics
conference and that is possibly the main
tension of that conference is we have
neuro scientists and we have I guess
Psychonauts and explorers and artists
and poets and all sorts and the tension
is between the materialist worldview and
one which is more centered on the
phenomenology of the experience and
mystery and faith not faith isn't quite
the right word but the religious
experience let's call it and I noticed
what I pick up from the extreme
materialists is a value system in which
internal experience and the claims or
the the value of internal experience is
lower than the value of
scientific reason always that those two
things there now I think they should be
on equal footing but in different
domains and serve different roles but
the smugness and the snide miss comes I
think from partly from that value
structure yeah I think this is a good
place to start the the second Jordan
Pederson clip because yeah I think it
talks to this sort of potential
dogmatism on the materialist side as
well so roll number two I read The
Spectator review of your recent
conversation I think you've now come to
the end of your debates for Sam Harris
and they said that you expressed a
little bit of irritation at some of the
when Sam didn't grass some of the points
that you were making or that you didn't
fully appreciate that he'd and
understood them I also think that Sam
Harris in particular like he's built a
whole kind of personality career several
books on this atheism position do you
think that he can argue in good faith
from that perspective could he turn
around and say well actually no you're
right Jordan this atheism thing is it I
think he was I think he was I think he
was conducting the discussion in good
faith I actually think that what Sam is
doing is a good-faith project you know
he I think there's conceptual muddiness
about it but you know his basic premise
is that we could come to an agreement
that working to reduce unnecessary
misery and suffering is a universal good
okay fair enough
that seems like a reasonable proposition
I don't think it's a proposition of fact
and he claims that it is but that
doesn't matter still it's fair enough
then and then you know so that's one
proposition another proposition is it
would be really good if our systems of
value weren't founded on air and what do
we have that's not air well we have
facts we have objective facts I mean
look at the technology look at what
we've done with our science it's like
you don't want to underestimate the
utility of objective facts so maybe we
can ground the value structure in the
facts it's like well that would be good
if we could do it so and and so and then
he
his ethic let's say is an amalgam of
those two propositions and I think that
his project is honorable and and and I
think he's committed to it he also
rightly is concerned with the dangers of
the fundamentalist dangers of revealed
truth and so is very skeptical about
about the axiomatic claims of dogmatic
religion it's like yeah fair enough but
his the mechanisms that he outlines to
derive values from facts are
insufficient in my estimation I don't
think that his argument is sufficiently
sophisticated even though I don't doubt
it's I don't think that Sam is any less
committed to an ethical good it's not
obvious to me that he is than I am
you know and he's argued and discussed
fully in good faith as far as I'm
concerned you know with the with the odd
error because no one is negotiating 100%
all the time in good faith I mean that's
a standard that no one can can achieve
but I think the discussions have been
unbelievably productive and and we'll
see that certainly the crowds are
responding I don't think the crowds
would have been engaged if Sam wouldn't
have been wouldn't been discussing in
good faith you know because the
engagement is actually an indication
that a good faith discussion is is
occurring otherwise it gets dull very
very rapidly we'll see what happens when
the videos are released
and that'll be in August once there the
sound is edited and all of that and and
then people will have a public debate
about how it how the discussion
proceeded I also think that each
discussion built on the previous one and
that we both ended up I think we both
ended up more informed and more
articulate than we started out so that's
a good that's a really good thing I
certainly understand his arguments much
better than I did well a year ago let's
say I think that exchange kind of
illustrates the point that I made I mean
like they asked him
whether sam harris was arguing in good
faith because if i mean if you look at
it from this perspective look sam house
is written like two or three books on
atheism he is one of the most kind of
noted celebrate' celebrity atheists with
possible exception richard dawkins so he
had a huge amount professionally at
stake so i guess my question about good
faith was is it possible for him to
change his mind and i was kind of
looking yeah i really didn't know what
what jordan would say about that i had a
sense that yeah that there was some
irritation sometimes in the way sam was
kind of caricature or or minimizing some
of the things that he was saying so i
was genuinely interested in whether he
thought that and genuinely kind of yeah
really interested in his response which
i kind of found to be like that there's
a this fan seemed to me to be a lot of
generosity in there it's like we all
really value sam's project i think it's
really good and a lot of honesty about
where he sees and conceptual modernist
and and all the rest of it but the
interesting thing for me is reading
below the comments on the leaked the
recently leaked talk from london and
I've seen this a few times like the Matt
Dillahunty talked with Peterson as well
I find this the material the sort of
atheist types to be far more dismissive
of Peterson Oh Sam destroyed Peterson
Peterson's avoiding arts answering the
question all of this I find them far
more dismissive of Peterson that I hear
Peterson being a Paris or generally
Peterson's fans being of Harris which is
interesting it kind of speaks to what we
said before the danger of a dogmatism in
the Atheist camp that can become a kind
of new religion yeah and as you're
saying that I'm something came up for me
which I thought in the past which is
when atheism does go that far
and it won't be all of his supporters
but it'll be you know some there is that
strand in the world when it does it
becomes a religion in a sense based on
being able to control everything there's
there's a real sense of that for me
because you know Peterson in that clip
talked about it will be good if our
values weren't based on air and that
really stuck with me
I was like hmm but going back to that
sense of we don't know where creativity
comes from we don't we don't know just
that with respect for the mystery
respect for the mystery and the ego
really doesn't like letting go into a
mystery you know that's that's part of
the inside of a lot of the Eastern
traditions as well so that kind of
strikes me as an interesting point
because I mean to be honest the irony is
the the pre-socratic philosophers they
were getting their information
Parmenides and pedak Li's they were
receiving their wisdom which became
logic from mysterious kind of
transcendent experiences so we have
based our values to a degree on what
they might call err but that that's
concept they might see as air is
actually something potentially very
different I would see it as something
potentially very different that it has
substance in it that there is some
substance that arises up that might be
the root of creativity or you know
whatever else we don't know but that
sense if we don't know there's a
humility in map and there's not very
much humility in we do know when it's
just a matter and anything we don't know
it's just a matter of time till we
figure it out with science yeah because
that's something that I've thought as
well it's like at some point your axioms
have to be or not have to be that your
axioms are based on something irrational
you cannot rationally derive axioms so
the idea that we can be purely rational
at some point you are making a leap of
faith you cannot avoid making a leap of
faith it's like what is your what is
your leap of faith going to be what are
your original axioms going to be you
have to kind of at some point assume
some things and so what are those things
and what was really interesting as well
in the in the o2 debate one of the
things Douglas Murray said which was
what we're seeing in the world seems to
be that when you remove religion people
will make new religions out of anything
and I think we're seeing this
particularly on the left at the moment
sort of like the whole equality
diversity what you might call didn't
call SJW thinking or has become a new
religion I think we're all kind of
this is there's there's a really real
dogmatism that seems to have arisen that
that is replacing the the old religious
stories and obviously also kind of
returning us to group identity and the
danger of that in terms of the
sovereignty of the individual and all of
that which which I talked about with
Jordan Peters in quite a bit more will
have coming up in one of our future
future videos what was also reminded of
there's a great line one of the guys
that we interviewed in America talked
about so scientism is this kind of
worldview that sort of sees Sciences as
the guys in their white coats the new
religion the guys and their white coats
and it happens at the very subconscious
level it's like you use scientific
validation to to support something like
oh the benefits of meditation oh it's a
dairy fairy thing no now that
mindfulness and we have these studies
and Dadda Dadda Dadda
suddenly it disease yeah it's the new
priesthood in many many ways but he had
this great line which was scientism is
more dangerous than jihadism because at
least you have ism how doesn't create
nuclear bombs science scientism has all
of the technologies or AI or any of
these things if you divorce science from
any kind of ethical and moral
responsibility and it's clearly not
obvious as peterson says how you
reintroduce it once you've once you've
got rid of it era seems to think that
you can so this is a crucial crucial
question once you've removed kind of the
ethical grounds which we could argue
Rupert Sheldrake and one of our videos
argued they're ultimately Christian in
origin but this ethical basis that you
take is self-evident sam harris is
actually based in a heart whole
christian story that's acted out through
our actions and through our assumptions
and it's it's a judeo-christian
worldview you get rid of that and you
don't get an emergent morality you get
science torn free of emergent morality
and that as yeah that is a terrifying
prospect yeah definitely and i murray
makes a really good i thought that was a
really good point by murray is round
that those new religions that we're
seeing effectively which are kind of
ideological kind of semi strange
political sjw style religions and and on
both sides in fact it's like they're not
based on what's come before they're
those the pp says the people who are
doing that they don't know what their
ancestors created before that is trying
to create this split and build something
on foundations that don't really exist
and that's that's quite a strong
argument for really engaging in religion
and seeing how these systems have
survived for so long and what tenants
they hold which is another subtlety
which was in the debate around religion
as a political institution
organized religion which I would be with
Sam Harris on around the massive
problems with that and religion as
Jordan Peterson talks about it which is
like looking at the deep archetypal
truth that exists within it which which
doesn't really cross over necessarily
with you know the Spanish Inquisition or
what the Catholic Church is up to in a
certain country yeah yeah and as
Peterson says Sam Harris in his books
and his lectures doesn't grapple with
Dostoyevsky doesn't grapple with
Nietzsche doesn't grapple with these
thinkers who wrestled with the human
condition and often resorts to a
caricature of religion that most
religious people don't believe yeah so
Sam if you're watching and you want to
respond to any of this you're more than
welcome your publicist of my details so
yeah let's let's look forward to what
we've got coming up and really exciting
like I was I was very taken with some of
Peterson's answers today particularly
about the relationship between the
individual and collective identity in
the left which I've never heard him mate
before and this I think will be the
centerpiece of what we're looking to do
next week because there's a I've seen a
few people on the left now really
grappling with Jordan Peterson in a kind
of sense of what does the left have to
learn from Jordan
and that seems new to me for a while it
felt like most of there's obviously the
radical death which hates women and
there's a kind of it there's the sort of
the soft left which is really unsure
about him and I had a sense for a while
that they were just wanting him to go
away and he hasn't been hey so now the
sense is okay and it's quite a brave
thing for people on the left to be doing
that because there's he's obviously
quite a kind of kind of polarizing
figure and an hated figure by some area
of the left so I would have kind of
acknowledged the bravery of the people
on the Left who are engaging with his
thought and what we want to do next week
is a whole series of programs looking at
what can the left learn from Jordan
Peterson yeah and I think it's a really
good timing I've noticed that sense of
something shifting on the left around
identity politics in particular and the
left kind of sorting its house out and
then last night there's a now quite
viral tweet of Barack Obama talking
about effectively the dangers of
identity politics and specifically using
Mandela as an example of someone who was
able to transcend that learned Afrikaans
in prison really you know challenging
and just disputing this idea of like oh
if someone's you know for example white
and male they can't possibly understand
you or you know just bringing back
empathy so Barack Obama bringing that
into the into the conversation I think
that's quite a big moment so I think
there is a kind of shift happening and
it's a good time great and any
housekeeping we've got a we've now
launched our podcast yes so our podcast
is also now available on Spotify so type
in rebel wisdom it's the one with our
logo not the one with one podcast in
February with a completely different
logo you can listen to that but um
haven't heard of it yet so yeah rebel
words of us on Spotify it's on pod bean
will put all the information down in the
show notes as well and subscribe to the
channel so that you can be kept in the
loop of the other Jordan Pederson clips
which would be probably coming up next
week and the whole series about Jordan
Peterson on the left and this could have
interesting crux point that we seem to
be out in the conversation around ident
politics if you've enjoyed this and want
to help us make more films please
consider sponsoring us on patreon again
the details are beat down there in the
show notes see you next week